daniel@arneam.com - https://www.linkedin.com/in/dmassis/ - https://github.com/medeiros

Summary

I have a master degree in Software Engineering and almost 20 years of experience working with web application development, Linux environments, enterprise software systems and Scrum agile method. Currently, I'm mostly focused on Scrum adoption and software architecture for distributed applications using Java-based technologies, adopting continuous integration and provisioning, but I also enjoy back-end and front-end programming. My approach to software engineering is methodical, minimalistic and evolutionary, aiming to keep things simple and extract simplicity and clarity from complexity and confusion.

- Software Engineer with 20 years' experience in software development, with technical publications in specialized Java magazine
- Experienced in working with Scrum onsite
- Focused on Agile, Java technologies, agile development, and design and testing techniques
- Interested in functional programming and front-end languages and technologies
- Motivated in working with Software Craftsmanship and Agile values, practices and techniques, such as TDD, Domain Driven Design, refactoring, clean code, user stories, continuos integration, Behavior Driven Development, and emergent architecture and design

Specialization Overview

Languages Java (J2EE); interests in Clojure

Operating systems Linux, MS-Windows

Internet / Web J2EE containers: Websphere, Tomcat, Weblogic

Distributed Systems REST, SOAP, EJB, JMS

Libraries Spring, JAX-WS/RS, Hibernate, JUnit, Hamcrest, Mockito, Maven Programming/Tools Javascript, CSS, HTML, AngularJS, Coffescript, Bootstrap, Git, IntelliJ

Databases Oracle; interests in MySQL and PostgreSQL

Agile Methods Scrum

NoSQL interests in MongoDB, Neo4j, Datomic

Cloud AWS IaaS knowledge

Professional Certifications

- Certified Scrum Master (CSM) Scrum Alliance São Paulo, 2013
- Oracle Certified Expert, EE 6 JavaBeans Developer São Paulo, 2012
- Sun Java Certified Programmer São Paulo, 2009

Professional Experience

Solution Consulting – Lead Consultant FICO

Nov 2017 - Present

In FICO, I'm working on development projects. Currently, I assumed a role of architect/developer in a small team, being responsible for architecture, design and construction of a multi-tier web application/batch processing solution, processing thousands of records per day under performance constraints, using technologies such as Java8, Spring

Batch, Univocity parser, Oracle database, REST/SOAP integrations, linux shell scripting, alongside with FICO own tools for rule engine and RAD in the front-end.

Bus & Technology Delivery Manager

Sep 2017 – Nov 2017

Accenture

In my brief passage through Accenture, I worked as manager and technical specialist. I supported teams in Scrum adoption and also worked in distributed software architecture, along with Digital front-end technologies. I also managed a digital architecture team for an internal project to a large bank.

Software Architect Consultant

Nov 2016 - Aug 2017

Octo Technology

In Octo, I worked with Software Architecture and Agile consulting for big enterprises. I was involved in projects related to microservices architecture (transition from monolith), CI (Jenkins pipeline automation), automated tests (culture, adoption and execution), and auditing (code quality analysis, approaches to improvement). I also conducted training of Agile Methods, and conducted multiple interviews with architect candidates.

Information System Specialist

May 2014 - Nov 2016

BNP Paribas Cardif

Technologies: Java, JMS ActiveMQ, Websphere 7, Spring (Core/Security/MVC/Test), JAX-WS, JAX-RS, JDBC, Hibernate, IntelliJ, SVN, Cygwin, Tomcat, Javascript, CSS, HTML, AngularJS, Thymeleaf, Lombok

- Helped in the adoption and execution of agile process to the development team, through adaptation of Scrum method to the internal reality of the company, considering matrix organization and plan-driven process
- Worked as Java Architect, setting internal patterns related to REST integration for the
 teams, providing design and architecture solutions to support functional requirements,
 and mentoring agile practices and quality aspects (automated tests, static code analysis,
 code review practices) into the teams;
- Worked as software programmer, in development and maintenance of Java Web Applications for the Intranet's company, using technologies such as Java, Spring, Maven, Websphere 7, Hibernate, REST, SOAP, ActiveMQ, Oracle.

Senior Java Developer

July 2013 – Apr 2014

BNP Paribas Cardif (hired by Spread Teleinformática)

Technologies: Java, JMS ActiveMQ, Websphere 7, Spring (Core/Security/MVC/Test), JAX-WS, JAX-RS, JDBC, Hibernate, Eclipse, SVN, Cygwin, Maven, SOAP

- Implementing Scrum in the software development area;
- Acting as a developer in a Scrum team, in development and maintenance of Java web applications to its internal clients (Intranet);

Software Architect Jun 2011 – Jul 2013

Petrobras (hired by Spread Teleinformática)

Technologies: Java, Weblogic 10, Spring (Core/Security/MVC), EJB3, JAX-WS, JDBC, JPA/ Hibernate, Eclipse, ClearCase, Maven, SOAP, Arquillian, Java Web Start, TDD, BDD, DDD, User Stories, Grooming, JSP, Oracle, Struts, JUnit

- Providing Intranet Java systems (web) to different areas of Petrobras;
- Acting in Scrum projects;
- Appliying techniques such as TDD, Refactoring, Continuous Integration, DDD, User Stories, Grooming, BDD;
- Setting the architectural/conceptual standard to the realization of automated tests with TDD and BDD;
- Acting is a project of mixtures movement between refineries, using EJB3, Java Web Start, JPA/Hibernate and grooming techniques to get clarity in the business requirements:
- Acting in a oil routes optimization project, using EJB3 with strong DDD usage in order to understanding of business rules;
- Acting in oil derivatives stock management project, using User Stories and Grooming to support the requirements elicitation;
- Support to the maintenance team in correction and evolution of several projects, using JSP, Oracle, Struts, JDBC, Hibernate, JPA, Spring, EJB 3;
- Supporting the hiring process of new developers (technical analysis)

Senior Programmer / Software Architect

Jun 2008 - May 2011

Petrobras (hired by Atos Origin / hired by BSI)

Technologies: Java, Weblogic 10, Spring (Core/Security/Webflow), JDBC, JPA 1.0/Hibernate 3, Eclipse, ClearCase, Maven, DDD, Oracle PL/SQL, JSF 1.2 (Rich Faces), Logback, JSP, JUnit

- Providing Intranet Java systems (web) to different areas of Petrobras;
- Definition of architecture and implementation of refinaries' oil stock management project, using Spring (Core 2.5, Webflow and Security), JPA 1.0/Hibernate 3, JSF 1.2 (RichFaces), Logback, Maven 2, and applying practices related to design and domain oriented development (DDD – Domain Driven Design);
- Improving the development process, by idealization and utilization of DDD concept into the IT area, in order to get a better business understanding from the development team;
- Supporting the maintenance team in corrections and evolutions in several projects, with JSP, Hibernate, Spring, Oracle PL/SQL.

System Analyst Jul 2006 – Jun 2008

Petrobras (hired by Accenture)

Technologies: HTML, CSS, Javascript, ASP, C# .Net, Oracle PL/SQL

- Providing Intranet Java systems (web) to different areas of Petrobras;
- Acting in oil derivatives stock management project, responsible for the maintenance of Oracle procedures (PL/SQL);
- Working in the software maintenance area, correcting and implementing new functionalities to several internal projects, using technologies such as HTML, Javascript, CSS, ASP, C#.Net;
- Architecture definition and implementation of industrial equipment protection control

Programmer Feb 2003 – Jul 2006

Agência Foster

Technologies: HTML, CSS, Javascript, Perl, MySQL, SQL Server, Oracle, Java, JSP, Servlets

- Developing Internet systems;
- Participation in a Java/JSP/Servlet project to Texaco intranet;
- Participation in Intranet, Extranet and Internet projects from medium to large companies, such as São Paulo Metro, Kodak, DuPont, Kraft, EDP, using technologies such as HTML, Javascript, CSS, Perl, MySQL, SQL Server and Oracle, being responsible for some projects

Languages

English – Advanced Spanish - Basic

Education

- Master' degree in Software Engineering, IPT/USP, São Paulo 2016
- BS Computer Science Universidade Metodista de São Paulo, São Bernardo do Campo Aug 2005

Publications

Testes unitários, de integração e de aceitação (Unit, Integration and Acceptance tests) Jan 2016 Java Magazine, 147

Dominando os testes automatizados (Mastering automated tests) Dec 2015 Java Magazine, 146

Modelagem e implementação com TDD e DDD (Modeling and implementation with TDD and DDD)

Oct 2015 Java Magazine, 144, p.14-26

Como adotar a análise estática de código (How to adopt static code analysis) Jun 2015 easy Java Magazine, 51

Independent Software Engineer

Open Source projects

Project: arneam-articles (@github: medeiros/arneam-articles)

July 2016 - Present

Opensource project to publish programming articles in the arneam.com website

- Main Language: Clojure
- Tech Stack: Leiningen, Ring, Compojure, Stencil, HTML5, CSS, Javascript, Bootstrap, REST, Atom (editor), microservices and hexagonal architecture concepts

Project: legislacao-ambiental (@: medeiros/legislacao-ambiental)

Jan 2016

Opensource project to crawl news regarding environment legislation

- Main Language: Java
- Tech Stack: NodeJS (npm), Gradle, Bower, Junit, Spring (Boot, Test) JSON, Yaml, Bootstrap, Angular, JQuery

Project: poc-jwt (@github: medeiros/poc-jwt)

Nov 2015 - Mar 2016

Opensource project to demonstrate JSON Web Token technology

- Main Language: Java
- Tech Stack: Spring (Security, Boot, Test), iharder, Jackson, Gradle, Lombok

Project: sbackup (@github: medeiros/sbackup)

Apr 2014

Opensource project to back up data

- Main Language: Scala
- Tech Stack: Java nio, Scala IDE, Maven, JUnit

Project: gpap (@github: medeiros/gpap)

March 2014

Opensource project to evaluate geometric and arithmetic progression calculations

- Main Language: Java
- Tech Stack: AWS PaaS (EC2, RHEL 6.5), Apache, Tomcat 7, TDD, Spring MVC, JQuery, JSON

Project: rAccounts (@github: medeiros/raccounts)

Sept 2013

Opensource project to manage personal passwords

- Main Language: Ruby
- Tech Stack: Ruby on Rails 4, AWS IaaS (EC2, RHEL 6.5), Apache, Passport

Technology Stack

Java 10+ years 10+ years HTML **CSS** 10+ years Javascript 10+ years 10+ years Oracle Scrum 8 years 8 years Spring Hibernate 8 years Maven 8 years **SOAP** 8 years Git 6 years 6 years JUnit 3 years **JMS** SVN 3 years REST 3 years Gradle 2 year Lombok 2 year AngularJS 2 year